<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[crypto | Gerlando Piro]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/blog/categories/crypto/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-16T10:10:56-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gerlando Piro]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cryptocurrency Cheat Sheet]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2014/02/11/cryptocurrency-cheat-sheet/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-11T21:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2014/02/11/cryptocurrency-cheat-sheet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Curious about Cryptocurrencies but not sure where to start? Here's a quick cheat sheet of resources to get you started.</p>

<h3>The Cryptocurrency Market</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.coinbase.com/?r=5297831b5446868b09000036">Coinbase</a> is a Bitcoin exchange located in San Francisco. They are one of the most well funded Bitcoin companies in the world and provide a high <a href="https://coinbase.com/security">level of security</a> around their services.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.cryptsy.com/users/register?refid=105115">Cryptsy</a> is a cryptocurrency exchange serving a huge number of coins. Cryptsy provides a crucial link in facilitating the conversion of alt-coins into Bitcoin.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.coinwarz.com/cryptocurrency">Coinwarz</a> lists the profitability of various cryptocurrencies. The calculations are done in real-time and are prone to wild swings so it's not the most reliable data, but it can serve as a good overview of the cryptocurrency market.</p>

<p><a href="http://bitcoinity.org/markets">Bitcoinity</a> provides simple Bitcoin value charts for various exchanges. This site displays the current Bitcoin value in your browser tab so it remains useful even when not in focus.</p>

<p><a href="http://bitinfocharts.com">Bitinfocharts</a> shows detailed information on the largest cryptocurrency markets. It's amazing to see how much larger Bitcoin is relative to everything else. The parabolic difficulty curve is even more impressive ;)</p>

<h3>Cryptocurrency Mining</h3>

<p><a href="https://litecoin.info/Mining_hardware_comparison">GPU Mining Hardware Comparison</a>: This is a reference list of results with various GPU and CPU hardware along with the config settings. You'll want a card with a high hash rate (kH/s) to power (W) ratio. The card with the best ratio available, the AMD 7950, is discontinued and close to impossible to find at a good price. The r9 280x and r9 290 are good alternatives that are much easier to find.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.cryptobadger.com/build-your-own-litecoin-mining-rig">Guide to Building Your Own Litecoin Mining Rig</a>: This guide was the template from which I built my rig. The specific set of parts he lists is nearly impossible to find, but this will give you an idea of what to look for.</p>

<p><a href="https://bitcointalk.org/index.php?topic=28402.0">Mining Software: CGMiner 3.7.2</a>: This is the reference thread for CGMiner, the software that will run your miner.</p>

<p><a href="http://middlecoin2.s3-website-us-west-2.amazonaws.com">MiddleCoin Mining Pool</a>: This is my go to pool. Middlecoin is an auto-switching pool that seeks the most profitable alt coins to maximize the return on your hashing power. It also auto-exchanges mined coins and pays out in Bitcoin (BTC). Better still, joining the pool is as simple as pointing your miner at it using a Bitcoin wallet address.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Calculating Cryptocurrency Mining ROI and Profitability]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2014/02/09/calculating-cryptocurrency-mining-roi-and-profitability/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-09T21:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2014/02/09/calculating-cryptocurrency-mining-roi-and-profitability</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have a simple way of calculating the time to ROI and profitability on my mining rigs. The formula is as follows.</p>

<ol>
<li><p><a href="http://bitcoinity.org/markets">Look up the current value of a Bitcoin</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Visit a auto-switching mining pool, my current favorite is <a href="http://www.middlecoin.com">Middlecoin</a>, and get the current BTC/Mhs/day rate.</p></li>
<li><p>Calculate the cost to build a rig that achieves about 1 Mhs/day. A good starting point is 3 r9 270xs, 2 r9 280xs, or 2 r9 290s. A full list of cards and hash rates can be found <a href="https://litecoin.info/Mining_hardware_comparison">here</a>. Then, start pricing parts. <a href="http://www.newegg.com">NewEgg</a> is a good place to start. You'll need a motherboard, cpu, ram, power supply, usb drive, and one or more video cards.</p></li>
<li><p>Now simply calculate ($Bitcoin_Value x $Bitcoin_per_Mhs) to get your estimated daily payout and $Rig_cost / ($Bitcoin_value x $Bitcoin_per_Mhs) to get your days till break even on your rig cost.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>This is a simple estimation which does not take into account volatility in Bitcoin value or an increase in mining difficulty, but I believe adding a projection of either is adding speculation upon speculation. The crypto currency market is not for the faint of heart, but at least this should give you a baseline expectation with which to plan and track your progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cryptocurrency Mining Update: January 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2014/02/02/crypto-currency-mining-update-january-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-02T21:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2014/02/02/crypto-currency-mining-update-january-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been a bit over a month since I started an experiment in mining Cryptocurrencies. One of the big questions I had going into it was wether or not mining could actually be profitable. In the time that I have been mining, daily payouts have been about 0.012 BTC/Mhs/day. That works out to about $10/day. In my <a href="/2014/01/02/a-small-mining-adventure-the-beginning">previous post</a> I mentioned a 1.2Mh/s rig cost $1260 to put together so, at the current average rate, my projection of a 4 month payback schedule was accurate.</p>

<p>Below is a chart of daily earnings since the beginning of the experiment.</p>

<p><img src="/images/january-update.png" alt="January Mining Chart" /></p>

<p>You'll notice a pretty good rate of growth. That's because I not only finished the build of my first rig, I decided to add a second rig and effectively double my hash rate. There was an additional spike in the last few days due to growth in Dogecoin which increased payouts to 0.017 BTC/Mh/day. I don't expect this to last long term, but it's interesting because it's a common assumption that profitability should fall over time due to increased difficulty. At least over the short term, this is clearly not correct.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A small mining adventure: The beginning]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2014/01/02/a-small-mining-adventure-the-beginning/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-02T21:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2014/01/02/a-small-mining-adventure-the-beginning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've been intrigued by the buzz surrounding Bitcoin since it spiked in value in early 2013 due to the near collapse of the Cyprus economy. A subsequent larger spike caused by increased interest in China finally caused me to go forward with building out a Litecoin mining rig and trying my luck as a small time miner.</p>

<p>The decision to mine Litecoin rather than Bitcoin was based simply out of accessibility. Bitcoin mining is extremely competitive and expensive nowadays. It also relies on specialized hardware often times from unreliable sources. Litecoin can still be mined effectively on standard computing hardware and exchanges such as <a href="https://www.cryptsy.com">Cryptsy</a> allow one to exchange Litecoin for Bitcoin.</p>

<p>I set out my plan with two main goals. Satisfying my curiosity around mining and breaking even financially.</p>

<p>With the help of <a href="http://www.coinminingrigs.com">CoinMiningRigs.com</a>, <a href="http://www.cryptobadger.com/build-your-own-litecoin-mining-rig">CryptoBadger</a>, and the advice of a coworker I pieced together the following components to build a computer for the first time since high school.</p>

<p>Here's what I ordered.</p>

<ul>
<li>GPUS - (2) MSI R7950 Twin Frozr</li>
<li>Power Supply - Cooler Master Silent Pro Gold - 1200W</li>
<li>RAM - G.SKILL Ripjaws X Series 4GB 240-Pin DDR3 SDRAM</li>
<li>Motherboard - ASRock 990FX Extreme3 AM3+</li>
<li>CPU - AMD Sempron 145 Sargas 2.8GHz Socket AM3 45W Single-Core Desktop Processor</li>
<li>Hard Drive - SanDisk ReadyCache 32 GB SSD</li>
<li>"Case" - White Plastic Storage Crate</li>
</ul>


<p>Scoping out components is an interesting challenge starting with simply finding a place that had the parts required! I just happened on a couple of 7950 GPUs which are highly regarded for their hash rate/power ratio. I should be able to get 1200kH/s at 600W.</p>

<p>The motherboard and power supply were both chosen with expansion in mind. Once the rig is up and running I should be able to add two more GPUs for a total of 2400kH/s.</p>

<p>The CPU, memory, storage, and case were all chosen to be inexpensive as they have little affect on hash rate.</p>

<p>The total cost for this build was $1260 and, at the time of purchase was expected to break even in about 4 months. I can lower the break even point to 3 months, and double my hash rate, if I invest another $800 to add 2 GPUs to the rig. Apparently you really do need to spend money to earn money.</p>

<p>Getting the rig up and running was a lot more difficult than I expected. Through a few frustrating days of trial and error I figured out one of the GPUs I received was bad and needed to be set for repair. This unexpected set back would cut my hash rate in half and push my time to break even out to nine months!</p>

<p>So I did what any rational gambler would do and I bought a 3rd GPU so I'd have at least two running full time while the third was sent away for repairs.</p>

<p>Thankfully the additional GPU plugged in and powered up without incident and I've been happily mining for about a week an a half. Simply getting the rig sourced, built, and running took longer than expected but once I started mining I discovered Litecoin wasn't the most profitable coin to mine. Lesson one was complete, but the education was just starting.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
