<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Gerlando Piro]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-30T21:04:55-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gerlando Piro]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Minimalist Blogging Stack]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/30/the-minimalist-blogging-stack/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-30T20:59:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/30/the-minimalist-blogging-stack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I alluded to in my initial $5 Web App Challenge post, I have not been a very active writer in the past. Over the years I&#8217;ve probably tried every blogging platform under the sun from hosted platforms like Blogger and Tumblr, to self hosted apps like Drupal and WordPress. Nothing ever seemed to click with me and I&#8217;d find myself spending my time yak shaving in hopes of progress. Inevitably I&#8217;d get frustrated and just give up, inspiration and motivation lost in the process. The solution, I found only recently, was to embrace constraints and simplify.</p>

<p>My current blogging stack consists of <a href="http://www.iawriter.com">IA Writer</a> (editor), <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> (blog), and S3 (hosting). It&#8217;s a developer friendly set up so non-techies might have to learn some new tricks, but learning how to DIY never hurt anyone! Next I&#8217;ll break down how each layer in the stack helps me work faster, run cheaper, and stay focused on writing.</p>

<h2>IA Writer</h2>

<p>IA Writer is a wonderfully simple iOS and OSX text editor built for the sole purpose of distraction free writing. The application has practically no chrome and a few features, but the features that are extremely handy. First off is <strong>focus mode</strong>, a feature that allows you to focus on the current sentence by greying out all surrounding text. Files can be saved to iCloud so they are available when inspiration hits on any device with IA Writer installed. The iOS version adds special keys to ease navigating through documents by word or character.</p>

<p>IA Writer also supports <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax#overview">Markdown formatted documents</a>. This last feature is pretty awesome as Octopress also supports Markdown so you can easily cut and paste documents into an Octopress file or    <em>edit your Octopress files directly with IA Writer</em>. If you work that way you lose iCloud sharing across devices, but it&#8217;s nice to have the option.</p>

<p>And finally, IA Writer has a preview window so you can see how your page will look before pushing it to your blog.</p>

<h2>Octopress</h2>

<p>Keeping with the simple theme, Octopress is a blogging framework that turns the Wordpress model of content management on it&#8217;s head. Instead of having managing content through a web application and pulling content form a database, Octopress generates a static version of your content on your local computer <em>before</em> pushing to a web server. There are numerous benefits to this technique including much better security, faster response times, and much lower web server requirements.</p>

<p>Octopress posts are simple text files that can be edited in any text editor and automated tasks handle static file generation and web server deployment.</p>

<p>Since the output of Octopress is static html and css, all you need is a web service that can handle static files, and that&#8217;s where S3 comes in.</p>

<h2>Amazon S3</h2>

<p><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/s3">Amazon S3</a>, or Simple Storage Service, has an intentionally minimal feature set for storing and retrieving static content. It&#8217;s very robust and extremely cost efficient with rates currently at $0.095/mo. for a GB of storage and $0.01 per 10,000 GET requests which means you can run a pretty well trafficked site for only pennies a month. The current version of Octopress does not come with support for deployments to S3 built in but it&#8217;s <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/pull/107">coming soon</a>. So you&#8217;ll need to come up with your own method for syncing to S3 for now.</p>

<h2>Wrapping Up</h2>

<p>My writing efforts are still in the nascent stage, but I&#8217;m really enjoying the technologies that have been chosen. I would love to hear what tools you use in your blogging efforts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting the $5 Web App Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-27T13:26:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>That&#8217;s not a typo in the title. I&#8217;m seriously challenging myself to pull in $5 in profit this year. Keep reading to hear why I consider this far from a trivial goal.</strong></p>

<p>I&#8217;ve been working as a web developer at various startups since the late 90s, and for many years I&#8217;ve dreamt of creating and selling a product of my own. I consider my design and dev skills to be decent but to date I have failed to launch anything of substance to call my own.</p>

<p>The cause is certainly not from a lack of good role models. I&#8217;ve been lucky enough to work beside some wonderfully smart and ambitious people that have gone on to do, and continue to do, great things. I&#8217;ve followed the rise of people such as <a href="http://unicornfree.com">Amy Hoy</a> since her Rails cheat sheet days, and more recently <a href="http://nathanbarry.com">Nathan Barry</a> with his Designing Web Applications book.</p>

<p>The new year brought upon a good deal of introspection as I read through a couple of books on the Lean Startup Methodology and behavioral marketing. I came to realize that I&#8217;ve been focused on the wrong things when it comes to building products and I let fear of ridicule hold me back from sharing my thoughts and experiences.</p>

<p>A couple of timely posts about <a href="http://lesseverything.com/blog/archives/2013/01/24/fear-just-refocuses-itself-1">fear</a> and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5119213">regret</a> have solidified my resolve to finally take action and launch something.</p>

<p>So taking a page from Nathan&#8217;s <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/starting-web-app-challenge">$5k Web App Challenge</a>, I&#8217;ve come up with a challenge that I like to call the $5 Web App Challenge. The goal of which is to create a product or service that generates $5 in profit by the end of the year.</p>

<p>It may sound like ridiculously low bar to set, but it will require me to complete three goals that have so far eluded me:</p>

<ul>
<li>Identifying a target customer</li>
<li>Building an audience</li>
<li>Creating something people are willing to pay for</li>
</ul>


<p>I will be leaning (no pun intended) on the process outlined in Ash Maurya&#8217;s <a href="http://runninglean.co">Running Lean</a> as a starting point and intend to adjust accordingly as I figure out what does and does not work for me.</p>

<p>Additionally, I committing to writing about the experience along the way in the hopes that someone finds it useful and to improve my quality and confidence in public communication. If you&#8217;ve read this far down the page please use the links below to get in touch or to follow my progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
