<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Gerlando Piro]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-04T08:54:59-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gerlando Piro]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalist Blogging with IA Writer, Octopress and S3]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/04/minimalist-blogging-with-ia-writer-octopress-and-s3/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-04T08:51:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/04/minimalist-blogging-with-ia-writer-octopress-and-s3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I alluded to in my initial <a href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge">$5 Web App Challenge</a> post, I have not been an active writer in the past. In years past, I&#8217;ve probably tried every blogging platform under the sun from hosted platforms like Blogger and Tumblr, to self hosted apps like Drupal and WordPress. Nothing seemed to click and I&#8217;d find myself spending time <a href="http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/yak_shaving">yak shaving</a> instead of writing. Inevitably I&#8217;d get frustrated and give up; inspiration and motivation lost in the process. The solution, I found recently, was to embrace constraints and simplify.</p>

<p>My current &#8220;blogging stack&#8221; consists of IA Writer, Octopress, and Amazon S3. It&#8217;s a developer friendly set up so non-techies might have to learn new tricks, but learning how to DIY is in itself very rewarding. In this post break down how each layer in the stack helps me work faster, run cheaper, and stay focused on writing.</p>

<h3>The Editor: IA Writer</h3>

<p>The biggest improvement in my ability to write has been finding an editor that suited me well. <a href="http://www.iawriter.com">IA Writer</a> is a wonderfully simple iOS and OSX text editor built for the sole purpose of distraction free writing. The application has practically no chrome and few features, but the features it <em>does</em> have are extremely handy. First off is <strong>focus mode</strong>, this feature allows you to focus on the current sentence by greying out all surrounding text. Files can be saved to iCloud you can write and edit on either iOS or OSX whenever inspiration hits. The iOS version adds special keys to ease navigating through documents by word or character.</p>

<p>Most important in my mind is that IA Writer supports <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax#overview">Markdown formatted documents</a>. This last feature is pretty awesome as the blog software I use, Octopress, also supports Markdown. This shared feature means you can easily cut and paste documents into an Octopress file or <em>edit your Octopress files directly with IA Writer</em>. IA Writer has a preview window so you can be sure your Markdown renders as you expect it to.</p>

<h3>The Blog: Octopress</h3>

<p>In keeping with the theme of simplicity, I prefer <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> as my blogging platform. Most blog platforms, such as Wordpress, are delivered as web applications. In contrast, Octopress is a static file compiler that generates your entire site on your local computer <em>before</em> pushing to a web server. Octopress does not require a web application to deliver or manage content and as such, benefits from better security, faster response times, and much lower web server requirements.</p>

<p>Octopress posts are simple text files that can be formatted with Markdown syntax and can be edited in any text editor. Site generation and web server deployment are managed through scripted Rake tasks.</p>

<p>Since the output of Octopress is static html and css, all you need is a web service that can handle static files, and that&#8217;s where Amazon S3 comes in.</p>

<h3>The Web Host: Amazon S3</h3>

<p><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/s3">Amazon S3</a> has an intentionally minimal feature set for storing and retrieving static content. It&#8217;s very robust and extremely cost efficient with rates currently at $0.095/mo. for a GB of storage and $0.01 per 10,000 GET requests which means you can run a pretty well trafficked site for only pennies a month. Amazon consistently improves service and prices in their efforts to dominate market share, so  S3&#8217;s value over time will only increase.</p>

<p>Octopress does not currently support deployments to S3 by default, but it&#8217;s <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/pull/107">coming soon</a> and there are some <a href="http://www.jerome-bernard.com/blog/2011/08/20/quick-tip-for-easily-deploying-octopress-blog-on-amazon-cloudfront">good articles</a> on how to DIY it for the impatient.</p>

<h3>Wrapping Up</h3>

<p>My writing efforts are still in the nascent stage, but I&#8217;m confident I have finally have a set of tools that match my preferred way of working. Embracing constraints and using a few simple tools has allowed me to focus on the task of writing and to publish on a reliable, robust web host for pennies a month.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting the $5 Web App Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-27T13:26:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>That&#8217;s not a typo in the title. I&#8217;m seriously challenging myself to pull in $5 in profit this year. Keep reading to hear why I consider this far from a trivial goal.</strong></p>

<p>I&#8217;ve been working as a web developer at various startups since the late 90s, and for many years I&#8217;ve dreamt of creating and selling a product of my own. I consider my design and dev skills to be decent but to date I have failed to launch anything of substance to call my own.</p>

<p>The cause is certainly not from a lack of good role models. I&#8217;ve been lucky enough to work beside some wonderfully smart and ambitious people that have gone on to do, and continue to do, great things. I&#8217;ve followed the rise of people such as <a href="http://unicornfree.com">Amy Hoy</a> since her Rails cheat sheet days, and more recently <a href="http://nathanbarry.com">Nathan Barry</a> with his Designing Web Applications book.</p>

<p>The new year brought upon a good deal of introspection as I read through a couple of books on the Lean Startup Methodology and behavioral marketing. I came to realize that I&#8217;ve been focused on the wrong things when it comes to building products and I let fear of ridicule hold me back from sharing my thoughts and experiences.</p>

<p>A couple of timely posts about <a href="http://lesseverything.com/blog/archives/2013/01/24/fear-just-refocuses-itself-1">fear</a> and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5119213">regret</a> have solidified my resolve to finally take action and launch something.</p>

<p>So taking a page from Nathan&#8217;s <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/starting-web-app-challenge">$5k Web App Challenge</a>, I&#8217;ve come up with a challenge that I like to call the $5 Web App Challenge. The goal of which is to create a product or service that generates $5 in profit by the end of the year.</p>

<p>It may sound like ridiculously low bar to set, but it will require me to complete three goals that have so far eluded me:</p>

<ul>
<li>Identifying a target customer</li>
<li>Building an audience</li>
<li>Creating something people are willing to pay for</li>
</ul>


<p>I will be leaning (no pun intended) on the process outlined in Ash Maurya&#8217;s <a href="http://runninglean.co">Running Lean</a> as a starting point and intend to adjust accordingly as I figure out what does and does not work for me.</p>

<p>Additionally, I committing to writing about the experience along the way in the hopes that someone finds it useful and to improve my quality and confidence in public communication. If you&#8217;ve read this far down the page please use the links below to get in touch or to follow my progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
