<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Gerlando Piro]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-28T09:01:17-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gerlando Piro]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting the $5 Web App Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-27T13:26:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>That&#8217;s not a typo in the title. I&#8217;m seriously challenging myself to pull in $5 in profit this year. Keep reading to hear why I consider this far from a trivial goal.</strong></p>

<p>I&#8217;ve been working as a web developmer at various startups since the late 90s, and for many years I&#8217;ve dreamt of creating and selling a product of my own. I consider my design and dev skills to be decent but to date I have failed to launch anything of substance to call my own.</p>

<p>The cause is certainly not from a lack of good role models. I&#8217;ve been lucky enough to work beside some wonderfully smart and ambitious people that have gone on to do, and continue to do, great things. I&#8217;ve followed the rise of people such as <a href="http://unicornfree.com">Amy Hoy</a> since her Rails cheat sheet days, and more recently <a href="http://nathanbarry.com">Nathan Barry</a> with his Designing Web Applications book.</p>

<p>The new year brought upon a good deal of introspection as I read through a couple of books on the Lean Startup Methodology and behavioral marketing. I came to realize that I&#8217;ve been focused on the wrong things when it comes to building products and I let fear of ridicule hold me back from sharing my thoughts and experiences.</p>

<p>A couple of timely posts about <a href="http://lesseverything.com/blog/archives/2013/01/24/fear-just-refocuses-itself-1">fear</a> and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5119213">regret</a> have solidified my resolve to finally take action and launch something.</p>

<p>So taking a page from Nathan&#8217;s <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/starting-web-app-challenge">$5k Web App Challenge</a>, I&#8217;ve come up with a challenge that I like to call the $5 Web App Challenge. The goal of which is to create a product or service that generates $5 in profit by the end of the year.</p>

<p>It may sound like ridiculously low bar to set, but it will require me to complete three goals that have so far eluded me:</p>

<ul>
<li>Identifying a target customer</li>
<li>Building an audience</li>
<li>Creating something people are willing to pay for</li>
</ul>


<p>I will be leaning (no pun intended) on the process outlined in Ash Maurya&#8217;s <a href="http://runninglean.co">Running Lean</a> as a starting point and intend to adjust accordingly as I figure out what does and does not work for me.</p>

<p>Additionally, I committing to writing about the experience along the way in the hopes that someone finds it useful and to improve my quality and confidence in public communication. If you&#8217;ve read this far down the page please use the links below to get in touch or to follow my progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
