<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Ruby TIL]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rubytil.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rubytil.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-21T11:09:00-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rubytil.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gerlando Piro]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instagram reverts Terms of Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/21/instagram-reverts-terms-of-service/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-21T11:05:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/21/instagram-reverts-terms-of-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Because of the feedback we have heard from you, we are reverting this advertising section to the original version that has been in effect since we launched the service in October 2010.</p></blockquote>

<p>Instagram is Facebook&#8217;s golden goose that&#8217;s yet to lay a single egg. I would expect this reversal of terms to be temporary and for the next update to  terms to much have less straightforward language</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Watch A Company’s Management Team Mutate]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/19/watch-a-companys-management-team-mutate/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-19T15:46:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/19/watch-a-companys-management-team-mutate</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>“When we joined this much larger company, it was difficult to understand where in the organization other people you met worked,” Matejka tells Co.Design. “So I started collecting the data initially to help us orient ourselves within our new company. After collecting the data on a daily basis for a little while, I figured it might be nice to look at the changes over time, and that is when the OrgOrgChart animation began.”</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Engineering RC cars from Dyson's scrapheap]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/19/engineering-rc-cars-from-dysons-scrapheap/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-19T10:41:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/19/engineering-rc-cars-from-dysons-scrapheap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wonderful story of designing within constraints.</p>

<blockquote><p>The engineering brief was to build a remote controlled vehicle out of Dyson Balls and a few spare parts found in Dyson’s research, design and development department.</p>

<p> Our team all had ideas around the engineering behind our vehicle but what led the design was the materials that were available. Our overall philosophy was robustness through simplicity so that there would be fewer points of failure and less chance of problems.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instagram's Awesome New Terms of Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/17/instagrams-awesome-new-terms-of-service/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-17T22:47:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/17/instagrams-awesome-new-terms-of-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I cancelled my Instagram account as soon as they were acquired Facebook. At the time the decision was based on a gut feeling that things would change for the worse. It turns out my gut was correct.</p>

<blockquote><p>To help us deliver interesting paid or sponsored content or promotions, you agree that a business or other entity may pay us to display your username, likeness, photos (along with any associated metadata), and/or actions you take, in connection with paid or sponsored content or promotions, without any compensation to you.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Want to See How Sausage is Made?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/16/want-to-see-how-sausage-is-made/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-16T19:50:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/16/want-to-see-how-sausage-is-made</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A meeting of Ruby implementation developers shines an interesting light on the process of developing a major programming language.</p>

<blockquote><p>&#8220;And I want to make sure as long as I live on this mortal
state, you need my approval before adding something as official
Ruby&#8221; &#8211; matz</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Don't Understand]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/16/i-dont-understand/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-16T18:34:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rubytil.com/2012/12/16/i-dont-understand</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ben Kamens of Khan Academy</p>

<blockquote><p>“I don’t understand” is the perfect response. You’re not insulting anybody. You’re not showing weakness. You’re building a culture of respect for how smart everybody is, because you know that after a few minutes of explanation you will get it.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
