<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Gerlando Piro]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-17T19:53:15-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gerlando Piro]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[LessConf 2013 : How Less Was More]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/04/16/lessconf-2013-how-less-was-more/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-16T21:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/04/16/lessconf-2013-how-less-was-more</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This weekend I was fortunate enough to attend LessConf in Panama City, Florida. What I experienced was a conference unlike any I have attended to date. A conference in which the hierarchy of organizer/speaker/attendee did not exist and where VC funded CEOs, bootstrappers, and dreamers alike were welcomed. A conference with a <em>genuine</em> sense of community in which everyone was given a safe harbor to show vulnerablity and discuss their experiences no matter how difficult they may be. This being the final LessConf a lot of people I spoke with were left wondering, &#8220;Where can we go that recreates this experience next year?&#8221;</p>

<p>Unfortunately no such place exists. <a href="http://www.twitter.com/stevenbristol">Steve</a> and <a href="http://www.twitter.com/allanbranch">Allan</a> created an event that came from the heart and reflected their unique personalities and values. These attributes showed themselves in large ways, such as Allan hosting 200 people (many like myself whom he had never met) at his house; and subtle ways such as Steve, not a small guy, going topless on the beach and encouraging others to do so.</p>

<p>There are countless intangibles that align to create a true sense of community among strangers, but four notable traits stand out as ones that increased the sense of community at LessConf.</p>

<h2>Less Information</h2>

<p>No speaker list, talk topics, or venue locations were released before or during LessConf. For social events the posted schedule simply listed &#8220;Secret Adventures&#8221;. As such, attendees came into the event with no preconceptions about who was talking, what their story were, where they were going to go, or what they were going to do. LessConf became a mysterious adventure for everyone involved. The lack of information sparked conversations and rumors among attendees that added to the fun and the sense of comradery as people tried to figure out what was going on.</p>

<h2>Less Distraction</h2>

<p>Intentional or not, the hotel chosen for LessConf lacked wifi. During the first day of talks, everyone was told to leave their laptops at the hotel though the venue <em>did</em> have wifi. When gripes started from a few that connected to the anemic network, Steve took to the stage and bluntly stated that he didn&#8217;t care about the wifi and that people shouldn&#8217;t be on their laptops anyway; and he was right. The lack of distractions during talks ensured that people were listening. The lack of distractions at all other times made people fully present for social interactions.</p>

<h2>Less Guarded</h2>

<p>Mixed in with the business talks were a number of extremely personal stories of adversity and triumph. <a href="http://www.twitter.com/ajleon">AJ Leon</a> shared how he found his true path in life by throwing away a lucrative career in the financial industry for a nomadic lifestyle traveling the world. <a href="http://www.twitter.com/ryanevans">Ryan Evans</a> discussed being jailed for insider trading in extreme detail. And <a href="http://www.twitter.com/greggyb">Greg Baugues</a> discussed his struggles with ADHD and Bipolarism. Each speaker&#8217;s story displayed vulnerability, strength, and perseverance that opened up everyone in attendance to converse on a deeper level and to share their own trials and tribulations.</p>

<h2>More Family</h2>

<p>LessConf was also unique in that the organizers and speakers had their families present. For many of us, family and quality of life are our motivation for working so hard. Seeing kids, spouses, and moms participating as integral members of the conference put everything into perspective and brought a warmth missing from other events.</p>

<h2>The Result</h2>

<p>Much of the value of a conference comes from the network of personal connections that are built. Allan and Steve crafted a place for those connections to happen at a faster pace and on a deeper level than any other conference I have attended prior. It&#8217;s something other conference organizers should aspire to. Not everything needs to be orderly and completely professional. There&#8217;s room for fun, and magic occurs in the presence of uncertainty. It&#8217;s sad to know LessConf is no more, but I&#8217;m appreciative for the time that was spent and the friendships I&#8217;ve made. Less was so much more than I can fully put into words.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Your Pitch Sucks]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/03/23/your-pitch-sucks/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-23T22:58:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/03/23/your-pitch-sucks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes selecting a software vendor is as simple as filling out a couple of online forms and hitting the ground running. Other purchases, such as ones with long contracts or high fees, require a bit more due diligence which normally comes in the form of an in person meeting. Unfortunately many of these meetings are a complete waste of time because of a crucial flaw in perspective.</p>

<h2>That&#8217;s so typical</h2>

<p>Here&#8217;s a typical pitch that occurs in conference rooms  everyday, see if it rings a bell. You&#8217;ve received a lead through your inbound channel and after some back and forth you&#8217;ve finally got an in person meeting with your prospect.</p>

<p>Upon arriving at your prospect&#8217;s office you make friendly introductions as you attach your laptop to the meeting room projector and fire up Power Point or Keynote.</p>

<p>Your presentation starts off with a generic stock image and copy explaining how things have changed in the &#8220;new world&#8221;. Next slide shows a leaky sales funnel complimented by a stock image of confused business person.</p>

<p>Next we see a chart and some venn diagrams. One shows how progressive business people are dealing with this &#8220;new world&#8221;. Now that venn diagram is overlaid with your product and how it helps every aspect of every problem ever known in business.</p>

<p>Everything is &#8220;higher&#8221;, &#8220;bigger&#8221;, &#8220;in the hundreds of thousands&#8221;. Your product is described with mystical jargon such as &#8220;machine learning&#8221; and top it off listing the &#8220;potential impact&#8221; to be 100%, 300%, 10x improvements.</p>

<p>Finishing up, you thank your audience and ask the ones who are still paying attention, if they have any questions.</p>

<h2>Wake me when it&#8217;s over</h2>

<p>If your pitch is anything like that, it sucks. Why? Because your presenting from the perspective of <em>your business</em> and not your prospect&#8217;s. In delivering a boilerplate presentation you missed out on an opportunity to speak directly your prospect&#8217;s pain points, and the full value your product can provide. You need to do better, otherwise you are just wasting hours of life that will never be recovered.</p>

<p>So how do you fix your pitch? It&#8217;s simple, just ask! Once your initial pleasantries are taken care of ask your prospect what they already know about your product. Listen to what they have to say and note where it differs from what you expected them to say. Next ask what business problems they are trying to solve with your product.</p>

<h2>And like magic&#8230;</h2>

<p>Now when you pitch make sure to reenforce the positive aspects your prospect already knew about and fill in the areas they were unaware of. Highlight direct examples of how your product can address the business problems they&#8217;ve brought up as well as ones they might not have considered.</p>

<p>By stepping outside of your world view and looking at things from the prospect&#8217;s perspective you&#8217;ll deliver a more effective pitch. One with an engaged prospect because instead of talking about solving the world&#8217;s problems, you&#8217;re talking about solving <strong>their</strong> problems.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Did Refer.ly pivot out of Zombie Startup status?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/03/13/did-refer-dot-ly-pivot-out-of-zombie-startup-status/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-13T09:07:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/03/13/did-refer-dot-ly-pivot-out-of-zombie-startup-status</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Danielle Morrill recently <a href="http://www.daniellemorrill.com/2013/03/zombie-startups">wrote about zombie startups</a> in reference to  Referly&#8217;s <a href="https://refer.ly/please-read-referly-discontinuing-rewards-paying-existing-links-through-march-31st/c/67f9d3fa890311e2bfbf22000a1db8fa#comments-container">pivot</a> from an affiliate link enabler to a blogging platform.</p>

<p>Refer.ly launched in June 2012 as a Y Combinator backed startup that made it easy for anyone to create and share affiliate links. It&#8217;s a novel idea but parallels can be drawn to Gumroad in that the main business model is an add-on service with extremely small margins. As I wrote in my <a href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/06/do-we-need-yet-another-stripe-checkout-app">analysis of Gumroad and other Stripe payment apps</a>, making a decent revenue stream, in this case one that can pay staff <em>and</em> satisfy investors, is extremely difficult unless you attain moonshot levels of growth.</p>

<p>In the Danielle&#8217; zombie post she illustrates the point, although not directly. Refer.ly&#8217;s <a href="http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8527/8545783275_14ae3b7e75_o.png">visitor growth</a> has been robust, but revenue was not. Clearly a change needed to be made to align their business with where they were gaining traction, unfortunately I think they&#8217;ve put themselves into a weak position but pivoting into yet another blogging platform. They&#8217;re entering a crowded market littered with high profile casualties such as <a href="https://blog.posterous.com/thanks-from-posterous">Posterous</a>, they still have no clear revenue model, and their new tagline, &#8220;A new kind of magazine for thoughtful shoppers.&#8221;, could only be more nondescript with significant effort.</p>

<p>When a startup pivots from a questionable revenue model to one reliant on page views and a sales you have to wonder how long until they pivot again or sell themselves as an aquihire.</p>

<p>One wonders if Refer.ly could have been successful if they had not taken the VC funded, quick growth approach. Fatwallet and RetailMeNot were both bootstrapped and generate revenue from affiliate fees. Without the pressures of VC money to grow fast or die, both grew organically and eventually sold for large sums of money.</p>

<p>In building my own product, a <a href="http://www.allthetags.com">tag management service</a> for online marketers, I have learned a lot by simply observing the path others have chosen. While I don&#8217;t agree with Refer.ly&#8217;s current course I appreciate how transparent they have been in sharing their experiences and hope it encourages more start ups to follow.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gems to use when crafting a Rails MVP]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/03/07/gems-to-use-when-crafting-a-rails-mvp/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-07T09:19:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/03/07/gems-to-use-when-crafting-a-rails-mvp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When creating a new web application there&#8217;s some basic functionality that you will probably want to add and get out of the way so you can start building out your core business logic. A lot of that functionality can be found pre-baked in the RubyGems ecosystem but the overwhelming number of gems, 52k and counting, makes it hard to know what to use and what&#8217;s crap. Here&#8217;s a list of useful gems to get your app bootstrapped so the real work can begin.</p>

<h2>Authentication</h2>

<p>Almost every web application needs user authentication and authorization capabilities. The gems below make it easy.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/devise">Devise</a></strong>: Devise is a flexible authentication solution that makes it easy to add user registration and login capabilities to your app. Devise has built-in Omniauth support so you can quickly integrate with 3rd parties such as <a href="https://github.com/arunagw/omniauth-twitter">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://github.com/mkdynamic/omniauth-facebook">Facebook</a>, and just about <a href="https://github.com/intridea/omniauth/wiki/List-of-Strategies">everyone else</a>.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/cancan">CanCan</a></strong>: CanCan is an authorization solution that works well with Devise and makes implementing access roles easy. All roles are defined in an Ability class that works with your User attributes to allow/deny access to your controller actions.</p>

<h2>Upload management</h2>

<p>If your users want to contribute assets, let them!</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/paperclip">Paperclip</a></strong>: Paperclip makes adding files to models relatively simple. You can configure image files for post-processing with Imagemagick. And out of the box Paperclip supports local file, S3, and fog storage with Azure and Dropbox available as add-on gems.</p>

<p><em>(alternative)</em> <strong><a href="https://rubygems.org/gems/carrierwave">CarrierWave</a></strong>: I have not used CarrierWave yet since Paperclip gets the job done. I&#8217;ve heard some say they prefer it over Paperclip so it&#8217;s worth checking out if Paperclip doesn&#8217;t float your boat.</p>

<h2>Payment Processing</h2>

<p>What&#8217;s the point in having customers if you can&#8217;t bill them?</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/stripe">Stripe</a></strong>: <a href="https://stripe.com/">Stripe</a> refers to itself as themselves as &#8220;Payments for developers&#8221; and so it&#8217;s fitting that they have an excellent api and robust tools to make it easy to integrate. You can also allow your customers to take payments through your site, although they need to have a Stripe account as well.</p>

<p><em>(alternative)</em> <strong><a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/activemerchant">Active Merchant</a></strong>: If you want to support multiple payment processors Active Merchant is the way to go. It provides an abstraction layer that supports a ridiculous amount of <a href="https://github.com/Shopify/active_merchant/wiki/gatewayfeaturematrix">gateways</a>. Active Merchant was a direct extraction from <a href="http://www.shopify.com">Shopify</a> so it&#8217;s been &#8216;battle-tested&#8217;.</p>

<h2>Frontend</h2>

<p>These make life easier for developers writing the view layer, and for users submitting text content.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/haml">Haml</a></strong>: <a href="http://haml.info">Haml</a> is an alternative syntax for html that, in my opinion, is WAY better to work with than plain HTML. Unlike HTML it&#8217;s whitespace sensitive and does not require closing tags. This does a good job of enforcing proper formatting habits and removes the mental overhead of closing tags in your more heavily nested pieces of layout.</p>

<p>I&#8217;ve interacted with some that absolutely hate Haml so it&#8217;s certainly a  personal preference, but I would suggest you give it a chance.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/github-markdown">github-markdown</a></strong>: Markdown is a lightweight syntax that makes writing and formatting text easy. Github&#8217;s variant adds a few changes to traditional <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown">Markdown</a> syntax and, since they use it extensively on Github.com, it should be well supported for the foreseeable future.</p>

<h2>SEO</h2>

<p>The grey area of the web&#8230;</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubygems.org/gems/friendly_id">Friendly Id</a></strong>: Rails surprisingly does not come out of the box with SEO friendly urls. Friendly Id fixes this by giving human-friendly strings to your data objects. You can choose one of the existing attributes in your model or pass in a generated slug. This is super handy if you want to have public, but obfuscated, urls.</p>

<h3>What are your picks?</h3>

<p>This is far from an exhaustive list, but it covers the gems I use most frequently. Now it&#8217;s your turn, <a href="http://www.twitter.com/gpxl">let me know</a> what gems you use to bootstrap your MVPs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lesson Learned: One Month into the $5 Web App Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/27/lesson-learned-one-month-into-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-27T22:28:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/27/lesson-learned-one-month-into-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&#8217;s been one month since <a href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge">I challenged myself</a> to launch a product with the goal of generating $5 in profit. I&#8217;m still in the research and planning phase, but I&#8217;ve already learned a valuable lesson for making progress in the early days of a new product.</p>

<h2>Share Early</h2>

<p>I have never had a hard time discussing product ideas with friends and colleagues, but when it came to soliciting feedback on my web app challenge I hesitated. My idea wasn&#8217;t fully fleshed out and I was worried I would be bothering people I respected with a half baked idea.</p>

<p>Regardless, I asked a few friends and colleagues to review my product idea and tried to validate the pain point I was trying to address. It only took a few conversations to realize that I needed improvement in how I communicated what the product did and what value it provided.</p>

<p>The great thing is that a few people stuck it through and helped  me iterate until my messaging was much stronger. Now I have a product pitch almost ready to test against a larger audience, but even more valuable are the connections I&#8217;ve strengthened with people I trust.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Overcoming Introversion Through Writing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/16/overcoming-introversion-through-writing/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-16T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/16/overcoming-introversion-through-writing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ever since I was a kid I have found communication difficult. I avoid picking up phone calls from unknown numbers and I stumble over words when talking with friends as I am constantly searching for the right way to say something <em>while I&#8217;m in the middle of saying it!</em> Now that I&#8217;m making an effort to document <a href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge">my experience building a web app</a>, it&#8217;s become clear that writing is a wonderful outlet for improving confidence in communicating and overcoming introversion.</p>

<p>In his book <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Influence-Psychology-Persuasion-Business-Essentials/dp/006124189X">Influence: The Psychology of Persuasion</a></em>, author Dr. Cialdini outlines six weapons of influence that are commonly used to create desired outcomes in their targets. These &#8220;weapons&#8221; trigger desired reactions due to cultural and social norms that subtly control our decision making habits. One such weapon, commitment and consistency, is described with the observation, &#8220;Once we have made a choice or taken a stand, we will encounter personal and interpersonal pressures to behave consistently with that commitment.&#8221; That is, once we have made a decision or taken action, we are predisposed to maintain that direction or ideal. Writing about an idea triggers creates and internal commitment and a need for consistency regardless of wether or not you believe what is written.</p>

<p>The knowledge of this behavior was used to great effect in World War II to gather secret information from American POWs held in China. Rather than torture and threaten their prisoners, the Chinese army would persuade them to write a statement that sympathized with China&#8217;s world view. This simple act of writing an idea down, an act of compliance, triggered a commitment to the idea. The need for consistency ensured that subsequent requests for compliance were accepted with greater and greater ease to the point where POWs freely shared military secrets with their enemy.</p>

<p>If commitment and consistency can have such a strong effect on American POWs, imagine what it could do if applied for self-betterment. It&#8217;s no accident that the very first post to this blog was a declaration of intent, to create a revenue generating web application. The act of writing and committing to an idea is a strong trigger and sharing that idea publicly deepens the commitment. Once that is achieved, the consistency principle ensures the need for follow through.</p>

<p>Overcoming introversion is difficult, but writing can be a powerful tool for self motivation. So take a stand on something, write it down, and share it with others. You may be surprised at the results.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do We Need Yet Another Stripe Checkout App?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/06/do-we-need-yet-another-stripe-checkout-app/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-06T17:01:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/06/do-we-need-yet-another-stripe-checkout-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wouldn&#8217;t it be awesome to create a service that would make it easy for anyone to easily sell digital goods online? That&#8217;s the thought that motivated me to start the <a href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge">$5 Web App Challenge</a>. But as I researched the market, doubt crept in. The ease with which a web application can be wrapped around <a href="https://stripe.com/">Stripe</a>&#8217;s payment api has already caused a mini boom in such services. With established players such as <a href="https://gumroad.com">GumRoad</a>, <a href="https://sellfy.com">Sellfy</a>, <a href="https://spacebox.io">Space Box</a>, and numerous others quickly crowding the space I began to wonder… do we really need another Stripe checkout app?</p>

<p>The appeal of creating such a site is strong as it fits a number of criteria I was looking towards when envisioning an app. The heavy lifting, payment processing, is off loaded to a third party. The MVP for the app is very narrow in scope. The market opportunity has been validated by the funding and competition already in the space. And there is clearly a need for such services in the number of <a href="https://gumroad.com/l/QVGo">high</a> <a href="https://sellfy.com/p/5ct4">profile</a> <a href="https://gumroad.com/l/DesigningWebApplications">creatives</a> already using them.</p>

<p>However, it&#8217;s not all unicorns and rainbows. The fees charged in this niche are extremely low, 1-2% per transaction (on top of Stripe&#8217;s 2.9% + $0.30 fee). A back of the napkin calculation shows that a run rate of nearly $2.5-5M is required to earn $50k/yr. With little to differentiate each other it will be difficult for any one service to charge a higher fee. That being the case, I would expect funded companies in this group to build their own payment systems to capture the 2.9% currently going to Stripe while continuing to target the general market for growth. The smaller players will need to go niche in an attempt to raise fees.</p>

<p>So no, the world does not need another Stripe landing page service, at least not one by me! Accepting this was tough as it set me back to square one with no idea of where to start. But doing so allowed new and better ideas to grow.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalist Blogging with IA Writer, Octopress and S3]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/04/minimalist-blogging-with-ia-writer-octopress-and-s3/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-04T08:51:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/02/04/minimalist-blogging-with-ia-writer-octopress-and-s3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I alluded to in my <a href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge">$5 Web App Challenge</a> post, I have not been an active writer in the past. In years past, I&#8217;ve tried nearmly every blogging platform available; from hosted platforms like Blogger and Tumblr, to self hosted apps like Drupal and WordPress. Nothing seemed to click and I&#8217;d find myself <a href="http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/yak_shaving">yak shaving</a> instead of writing. Every time I would get frustrated and lose inspiration and motivation. The solution, I found recently, was to embrace constraints and simplify.</p>

<p>My current &#8220;blogging stack&#8221; consists of IA Writer, Octopress, and Amazon S3. It&#8217;s a developer friendly set up so non-techies might have to learn new tricks, but learning how to DIY is in itself very rewarding. In this post break down how each layer in the stack helps me work faster, run cheaper, and stay focused on writing.</p>

<h3>The Editor: IA Writer</h3>

<p>The biggest improvement in my ability to write has been finding an editor that suited me well. <a href="http://www.iawriter.com">IA Writer</a> is a wonderfully simple iOS and OSX text editor built for the sole purpose of distraction free writing. The application has practically no chrome and few features, but the features it <em>does</em> have are extremely handy. First off is <strong>focus mode</strong>, this feature allows you to focus on the current sentence by greying out all surrounding text. Files can be saved to iCloud you can write and edit on either iOS or OSX whenever inspiration hits. The iOS version adds special keys to ease navigating through documents by word or character.</p>

<p>Most important in my mind is that IA Writer supports <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/syntax#overview">Markdown formatted documents</a>. This last feature is pretty awesome as the blog software I use, Octopress, also supports Markdown. This shared feature means you can easily cut and paste documents into an Octopress file or <em>edit your Octopress files directly with IA Writer</em>. IA Writer has a preview window so you can be sure your Markdown renders as you expect it to.</p>

<h3>The Blog: Octopress</h3>

<p>In keeping with the theme of simplicity, I prefer <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a> as my blogging platform. Most blog platforms, such as Wordpress, are delivered as web applications. In contrast, Octopress is a static file compiler that generates your entire site on your local computer <em>before</em> pushing to a web server. Octopress does not require a web application to deliver or manage content and as such, benefits from better security, faster response times, and much lower web server requirements.</p>

<p>Octopress posts are simple text files that can be formatted with Markdown syntax and can be edited in any text editor. Site generation and web server deployment are managed through scripted Rake tasks.</p>

<p>Since the output of Octopress is static html and css, all you need is a web service that can handle static files, and that&#8217;s where Amazon S3 comes in.</p>

<h3>The Web Host: Amazon S3</h3>

<p><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/s3">Amazon S3</a> has an intentionally minimal feature set for storing and retrieving static content. It&#8217;s very robust and extremely cost efficient with rates currently at $0.095/mo. for a GB of storage and $0.01 per 10,000 GET requests which means you can run a pretty well trafficked site for only pennies a month. Amazon consistently improves service and prices in their efforts to dominate market share, so  S3&#8217;s value over time will only increase.</p>

<p>Octopress does not currently support deployments to S3 by default, but it&#8217;s <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/pull/107">coming soon</a> and there are some <a href="http://www.jerome-bernard.com/blog/2011/08/20/quick-tip-for-easily-deploying-octopress-blog-on-amazon-cloudfront">good articles</a> on how to DIY it for the impatient.</p>

<h3>Wrapping Up</h3>

<p>My writing efforts are still in the nascent stage, but I&#8217;m confident I have finally have a set of tools that match my preferred way of working. Embracing constraints and using a few simple tools has allowed me to focus on the task of writing and to publish on a reliable, robust web host for pennies a month.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting the $5 Web App Challenge]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-27T13:26:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.gerlandopiro.com/2013/01/27/starting-the-5-dollars-web-app-challenge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>That&#8217;s not a typo in the title. I&#8217;m seriously challenging myself to pull in $5 in profit this year. Keep reading to hear why I consider this far from a trivial goal.</strong></p>

<p>I&#8217;ve been working as a web developer at various startups since the late 90s, and for many years I&#8217;ve dreamt of creating and selling a product of my own. I consider my design and dev skills to be decent but to date I have failed to launch anything of substance to call my own.</p>

<p>The cause is certainly not from a lack of good role models. I&#8217;ve been lucky enough to work beside some wonderfully smart and ambitious people that have gone on to do, and continue to do, great things. I&#8217;ve followed the rise of people such as <a href="http://unicornfree.com">Amy Hoy</a> since her Rails cheat sheet days, and more recently <a href="http://nathanbarry.com">Nathan Barry</a> with his Designing Web Applications book.</p>

<p>The new year brought upon a good deal of introspection as I read through a couple of books on the Lean Startup Methodology and behavioral marketing. I came to realize that I&#8217;ve been focused on the wrong things when it comes to building products and I let fear of ridicule hold me back from sharing my thoughts and experiences.</p>

<p>A couple of timely posts about <a href="http://lesseverything.com/blog/archives/2013/01/24/fear-just-refocuses-itself-1">fear</a> and <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5119213">regret</a> have solidified my resolve to finally take action and launch something.</p>

<p>So taking a page from Nathan&#8217;s <a href="http://nathanbarry.com/starting-web-app-challenge">$5k Web App Challenge</a>, I&#8217;ve come up with a challenge that I like to call the $5 Web App Challenge. The goal of which is to create a product or service that generates $5 in profit by the end of the year.</p>

<p>It may sound like ridiculously low bar to set, but it will require me to complete three goals that have so far eluded me:</p>

<ul>
<li>Identifying a target customer</li>
<li>Building an audience</li>
<li>Creating something people are willing to pay for</li>
</ul>


<p>I will be leaning (no pun intended) on the process outlined in Ash Maurya&#8217;s <a href="http://runninglean.co">Running Lean</a> as a starting point and intend to adjust accordingly as I figure out what does and does not work for me.</p>

<p>Additionally, I committing to writing about the experience along the way in the hopes that someone finds it useful and to improve my quality and confidence in public communication. If you&#8217;ve read this far down the page please use the links below to get in touch or to follow my progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
